okay
uh
so we're at this point where uh pabankar
and Britain encourages us to
make a little personal mantra for
ourselves
to remember
uh
taking away other people's problems and
giving them help
and then he's there's an ancient
tradition
of
saying a mantra to yourself okay and
just as you go through the day
so uh keep your Mantra okay don't lose
it when you
when you get on the airplane don't leave
it at the airport
okay and use it okay just use it while
you're walking around
I'll give a hundred dollars
everybody wakes up
uh if you can tell me the two
requirements for a powerful mantra
traditional requirements
for a mantra
that's it
I'm going to be great
all right no no I'm kidding I'm kidding
I'm kidding no you got it you got it I'm
just joking you
yeah
keeping your morality yourself and
getting the Mantra from an authentic
person yeah nice hundred dollars
how do you get your hundred dollars when
you win a bet in here
you go to in general you don't complain
to me two years later that you didn't
get your money okay
all right yeah uh
you have to
the Mantra has to be you have to be
encouraged by an authentic lineage to
create your Mantra and you did that
already and then secondly you have to
keep your
morality but mainly your ten good deeds
okay but also your other two kinds of
morality Rich for a hundred dollars are
what
yeah
yeah uh bodhisattva morani and and uh
you're tempting morally okay Diamond Ray
okay
don't forget to collect okay
all right um
uh and it means uh keep reciting your
little Mantra to yourself
so you can remember
to give people happiness and take their
problems
and you can do it in little tiny ways
like
like at the airport you can
let people get in line ahead of you at
customs and stuff like that okay
all right uh he gives a couple of
examples of mantras we talked about them
already
and uh I'm gonna
start at de la okay okay so a couple of
couple keep going there you go
yeah
he says look I could give you some words
from Golden Light Sutra
that suvana prabhas Sutra
that you could use for your little
Mantra okay
and again that that uh Sutra is it has a
lot of amazing stories about Lord Buddha
how he became a Buddha
the story of him giving his body to the
Tiger
is in there and uh
in Mongolia so we we've done a lot of
work in Mongolia John Brady has
three projects in Mongolia uh trying to
catalog and save 300 000 books
and um
I think if you ask a Mongolian what's
their greatest book ever they would say
the Golden Light suture so that's for
them very important
he says look
I could give you some uh Mantra from the
Golden Light suture but kyung
tirang machine
he says but you know you guys don't
really know those
that Sutra very well so then
so you could just recite the verse that
we got you from the llama chipa okay
which we do every time we do Retreat
here we the first night we get here we
do llama chippa so he says you could
just use the verse from Lama okay
he says
uh
some teachers of the past have used this
verse from the Lama Choppa
to do their uh
as a mantra
and instead of doing Vegeta mantras and
Retreat or something instead of doing a
hundred thousand budget getting mentors
or a million
mantras they will do this verse about
love
as a mantra like a million times or
something so don't do it as their
as what they're counting okay they'll
repeat it over and over okay
uh I have a
a picture for you you ready
nah go back to
43.22
there's two of them
yeah here's one uh llama super important
uh he passed away yesterday
uh
and uh
I just wanted to talk about him a little
bit
he uh he was the first person to invite
me to teach
in my life uh and he was a
a very great uh teacher
who helped bring
Buddhism to the West okay
and uh
the fact that we have Buddhism in the
world I mean I grew up in a country
where we didn't know what to Buddhism we
never heard of meditation
and there were a few great
teachers
who
you know came down a great suffering
came out of uh Tibet
lived in refugee camps and then slowly
came to the West
and there were just a handful
a very uh Brave teachers and they
learned English and they they helped
westerners and uh
I whenever I think about that those
years
I feel like it was the Titanic hitting
the iceberg you know and the westerners
were kind of like the iceberg
and then these few Brave teachers from
uh Tibet
uh came out of Tibet and started coming
to the west to teach westerners
they were kind of like the Titanic and
they kind of wore themselves out on the
westerners
it was not easy it was a huge
cultural Gap
between old Tibet and
and the west and these people these few
uh special llamas
uh came they came and they they tried to
teach crazy hippies I'll show you his
teacher Nama Yoshi next picture
that's a llama symptoms teacher
and they came out together and Lama
yeshi was a geshe
uh in the who came to the refugee camps
in
he was very goofy and you can see right
and uh he was a great Joker uh I
remember the story that uh
he he went to uh some Department Store
in San Francisco and uh
he said take me to the ladies section
and uh the students are all like what
and he said take me to the lady section
and he went to the lady section and he
found some like
really loud orange
and he said that's the right color
and then he bought them and he would
wear them and uh
and he's like done he was so goofy and
he taught at San Francisco State I think
University
uh he taught uh westerners so some of
the first Dunes
Tibetan Buddhist to to bang into the
iceberg of America
uh was Lama yeshi and it was hard for
them
it was really hard for them and they
they didn't have any money and uh
they were trying to teach
he he was teaching at San Francisco
State University I believe it was San
Francisco State
during the hippie times during the worst
part of Berkeley you know
and and it was so uh it took so much
courage
[Music]
Wild
hippies
about Buddhism and and he did and they
did and they tried really hard uh
and I remember uh one day
it came together to see my teacher
uh so it was a big deal you know so I
was all excited and um
and they came to the Mongolian Monastery
and uh
they showed up and um
and Lama yes she was Goofy and and fun
and Mama something was a hundred percent
the opposite
he was very very serious
and he was a very high uh reincarnated
llama
so he wasn't a geisha he was a
truku he was a reincarnated lover
and he was born on the slopes of Mount
Everest
he's from a village on Mount Everest in
the Tiny Village
and he so he ended up in a refugee camp
super conservative
uh and his only thing was to see how
many tantric initiations he could
collect
and I think he got up over a hundred
like I have three or something and uh
and he was very devoted to that
um
so he was a high high reincarnation from
the age of three or something
and
there was this magnetism
uh between them and
they built the largest uh organization
of
Western Buddhists in the world together
and uh
and they worked really really hard Mama
yes she had a heart problem
for many many years and uh he just kept
going and he refused to rest and finally
his heart gave out
his student love myself uh kept going
for many years and he had a stroke about
seven eight years ago
and he wouldn't stop and
when I did my sphere which feet
I I was teaching at his Center in
borgaya I was teaching Diamond Cutter
suture for the first time in
and he asked me to teach it and uh
so he was there and and uh
he didn't sleep he met students all
night uh
and I I said yummy advice for my
three-year Retreat and um
and I didn't hear back and then suddenly
his somebody's banging on my door at
like three o'clock in the morning he's
ready to see you and I'm like okay
and I went there with Christy and my
partner and and he
he said okay you guys are doing three or
between you know and we said yeah
and he said
um Your Eyes Ears Nose your senses
are the
are the man the retreating man
and the objects of the in the universe
the things to see things to hear things
to smell these are the lady
and they will be connecting the whole
retreat
and then he says good luck
I'm like
it was like he's amazing in
and he was very very conservative and uh
but he had a very for me
uh
he had an instinctual uh Democratic
spirit
and he would say look that's not the way
I would do it but I respect that you can
do it that way
and I I support you
and that's the way he was
so we lost a great teacher
and that uh generation is passed
I think that generation has passed so
so we're really lucky
to have the the
now it's kind of our problem okay no
it's our job
okay
so
he has Brave as him
in the
hard-working okay
keep keep
and so bless me my holy llama bless me
love
well I'm out of compassion
every living being there is
may find every kind of happiness
let all the evil deeds and obstacles let
all the pain that ever comes to
everything
every every one of them my mother
come and write better part myself
wrapping upon me now
and let any goodness I ever do in all my
happiness be sent away to other people
okay
uh there must say uh d-e-r-m-e down a
little bit
yeah
okay some
hell Topsy towards are gushing
uh use every
uh every activity of the day I I always
think of driving back to Tucson use it
as a practice okay
your interaction with the other drivers
which can be interesting in Arizona
uh
you know
use it as an excuse to
practice don't learn okay
even the traffic
through guys
then he refers to a couple centers that
you could check
foreign
the
King of the Dharma group he says you can
use it to see examples of that
okay uh
then he says okay
uh this Loom is an important word in in
Buddhism okay lung means uh in tibetan
wind
okay so it's one of the elements
earth water fire and wind sometimes
they'll add wood or consciousness
so long means uh wind
but it's also the word for wind in
tibetan is also the Tibetan word for Chi
a Prana okay so uh
we're getting into a very deep Diamond
way principle here in the long rim
and LOM Rim is a sleeper
sleeper in English means uh
it looks like it's just a dull long book
uh but there's Tantra running underneath
uh like uh water under the ice you know
and if you
really understand lamrim it's a whole
Diamond way teaching
for how many years now 13 years okay
been a diamond weight teaching under the
ice
okay and uh here the water comes up
above the ice okay
means
[Music]
a let it ride on your Prana
let the Tomlin
ride
on your Prana okay yeah
it goes very deep it goes very deep here
the the connection
between giving and taking the practice
of giving and taking taking other
people's problems
giving other people the good things that
come to you
that becomes a diamond way a tantric
practice okay with your Prana using your
Prana your breath is not your Prana
uh but your Prana is connected to your
breath very very intimately okay
so where it goes your breath
so goes your Prana okay so uh Tong LAN
is uh becomes a a pranayama
means a practice of
when you call it like
[Music]
um
making effort to make something happen
inside of you is I am okay pranayama or
it can also be read as control of your
breath ayama
Yama means control
and it also means the Lord of death
I'll tell you why
why uh in the old days Yama meant the
two Reigns of a
of a horse uh the two Reigns that you
pull the horse with
and so uh Yama came to mean a pair
of two things and uh
and in the ancient times there was a
pair of Night and Day
and there was two deities connected to
them and uh
Knight was supposed to represent uh
I think it's the loss of a of a loved
one
okay and and so it was uh
a pair nine and day were a pair like uh
like the reins of a horse which are Yama
so the Lord of death came to be called
uh Yama okay and uh if you kill the Lord
of death it's
you put an end to him Antica
okay
uh to kill the Lord
which is uh which we practice here and
and you can learn it okay what's the
other sounds good word for you Montica
name
yeah beat Death to be death to death
death be death to death call it thunder
okay all right and that's part of the
Hatha Yoga predipika
which is a very deep Retreat practice
text
it takes two years to teach it
and we're in the middle of it so come to
the next YSI program
in
when is it
September oh
and we're studying khaledunda that's the
whole topic how to kill death okay
all right so anyway here
uh
use The Prana
uh use your your breath practices
and there's obviously a deep connection
between your breath and your state of
mind right
when you get scared you're like
uh when you're too busy all day and
you're not focusing on people you're
also breathing irregularly
so if you want to know how your thumb
lens going
day-to-day hour to hour
you can check your breathing
how's your breathing and if you're
really
practicing giving and taking
on the hour to hour basis
it'll be reflected in your breathing
okay
okay so keep an eye on your breath
and when your breath gets uh jerky or
out of out of flow out of sync it means
there's something wrong mentally
okay
when you're
doing dongland hour to hour with your
little mantra
you're you should be doing pranam at the
same time
and your breath your breathing should be
sweet
and calm and regular going in through
the
left nostril exiting through the right
nostril you don't have to remember it
all the time you're not a bad person if
you breathe through both holes
okay
I had a student many many years ago
Nigel did you know him
from Burma
and
every time I taught him some little
thing like this he'd say no no don't
teach me anymore
and I'd say why and you say it's just
something else to feel guilty about you
know every time you give me a new
practice I and I don't do it I feel
guilty and I'm just like
driving me nuts I feel guilty all day
and you got to be careful with that okay
take the
take the instructions from Retreat that
struck you
that seemed cool to you
and use them for a couple weeks okay and
frankly let the other ones
go okay you can't remember everything
you can't practice everything
try to practice everything you'll
definitely your breathing will get
messed up against
so
so kinda
why does guessler teach hundreds and
hundreds of practices
yeah
act with one of them
and use it for a while so don't feel
guilty don't get overworked Dharma
overworked
choose the one that fits you
the reason they give hundreds of
practices
is that there's hundreds of
personalities
different people Different Strokes for
different folks
okay when you hear something that's
attractive to you
then practice it and don't try to don't
go crazy trying to do everything you
hear in these classes okay
I think
this pranayama connected to a Tomlin
Mantra connected to uh
whole day long habit of watching out for
other people what do they want what do
they need little stuff
opening the door serving them tea
you know uh I think watching other
people little stuff
and then Prana watching your breath as
you do it in uh and having this
intention
that that should make you a high
bodhisattva this little practice of
serving people tea opening doors for
people helping out people at the airport
stuff like that strangers right I I've
been uh Veronica and I and I'd like to
thank Veronica for coming today
uh
[Applause]
my my stepmom had a stroke it seems and
we we went to the nursing home facility
rehab
and uh
and there's you know there's hundreds of
people there
in the same
also in a bed there in uh
he started to talk to the other families
and it was so sweet it was so cool and
uh it felt like Buddhism
you know and normally I'm really shy
I'm not shy to teach but I'm shy in
public
with strangers and Veronica's like oh
where are you guys from and I'm like
you know and uh so all these families
were there and taking care of their
mother and uh
and then there was this beautiful Tomlin
going on you know so
the place to practice is
Wherever You Are
and you can do Tomlin everywhere then
connect it to your breath when you
remember
and that means when your breath gets out
of whack
something's happening to you okay when
you're breathing irregularly
you know either you're worried or
I don't know you're upset or you're just
not mindful
your breath will will not be smooth okay
so he says watch your breath and that's
a sign of how your care of others is
going
okay day to day hour to hour okay
okay say
when you get pretty good at Tomlin oh
cheered
uh when you breathe out remember you are
giving
kindness and help to other people
you are when you when the inhale
you're taking people's problems away so
don't miss the opportunity
to focus on taking away other people's
problems and giving them hell
as long as you're breathing you can do
it okay
are here the last The Last Word Jar
jar means connected to your breath
connect your practice to your breath so
then your breath will remind you to do
your thumb all day long okay
all right
um now I'm ready for that cowboy
spend too much money
forget it hundred dollars tell me why
the cowboy is relevant here
I think
so why is the cowboy on the horse
relevant for our discussion today
it's relevant because it's about long
Sam jackpot chica nice how The Prana and
the thoughts rise together just like the
Cowboy and the horse nice nice perfect
okay
[Applause]
don't forget to collect your cowboy
money uh
I was in China I was in Shenzhen uh
somebody was opening a new office they
asked me to do some calligraphy
and uh and I was thinking I needed
something like three four words
I chose sugangets in the next paragraph
in the Bold
uh in the bold letters right there
okay please repeat
one more time
tantric practice
here in the
lamrim for beginners
beginners
okay
so uh you've heard me say it many times
in yoga classes YSI loves lungsem
dupatti
and here it is you know people ask me
how to spell it and stuff like that well
here it is okay
so lung means that word for uh wind okay
Prana or Chi
all right
Sam means
the mind
s they flow together
okay they flow together like uh and the
the classic example is
a cowboy
on a horse okay we were
I heard some amazing news here in Bowie
the only functional business is a gas
station
and uh
and uh they used to have a 31 Flavors
there which was the only happiness we
had here
and uh it's an ice cream store
and we used to go there
you know it was a pilgrimage we didn't
go to the stupa we went to the ice cream
store
and then they closed it it was really
depressing and uh
and then recently uh
they opened it up again as an Indian
restaurant which is like a miracle
uh because I grew up on this and by the
way they're from
HP up area which is exactly the Indian
food I grew up on
uh and they make it exactly like I had
it 50 years ago
in India India and so it's it's kind of
a
a beautiful thing
and we used to go hang out there at the
ice cream store
and these guys ride up on a horse
and get off the horse and tie it to the
uh tie it to the
the pole there you know I was with
Jordan Cohen and Woody coin
from Israel
and uh we're having the ice cream and
the Cowboys right up and tie the horse
and they got these big guns you know and
uh here's the order I was like this is
they are making a movie right they are
making money I said you're them like
this is not the movie This is the real
thing remember
and he's like
you know she has a real button in the
gun I said yes
you also be nice to them
you know so uh we got Cowboys here
our neighbors are the last Cowboys in
Arizona or something
and uh be nice to them
don't don't
piss them off okay uh because they do
carry around I asked the guy why are you
carrying these two
big guns around he says he shoots
rattlesnakes for fun
and he got 25 this year and and I'm like
okay
that's nice uh and uh
so think about a cowboy okay and the
point is that The Prana and the
intention to be helpful to other people
are riding
uh like a cowboy on a on a horse okay
who's the horse and who's the cowboy
for 25 because there's only two choices
and I get confused sometimes frankly
who's the horse and who's the cowboy
this is the breath good the horse is
your Prana okay and who's the cowboy the
Cowboys you're mine yeah your feelings
are your intentions okay so the the
horse
is The Prana or the inner wind
which is reflected in your breathing
okay the inner wind is not smooth
your breathing will be jerky okay and
they make jerky
foreign
turkey is some
it's like chewing gum made from cows cow
meat
Bowie is the capital of jerky in the
whole world
so anyway
the horse is your bro okay and the
writer is your thoughts and specifically
your awareness of thumb land all day
okay like every chance you get
take care of somebody else okay every
chance you get
do something nice for somebody else
and
and there's this uh
deep
inner hesitation
to take care of other people first you
know you can force yourself if you're if
you've been in Buddhism class for 25 30
years
you can force yourself to take care of
other people first
and it's difficult uh it feels like an
obligation
and sometimes you let it go and you take
the thing first and it feels really good
to take care of yourself first
you know and you're like a few
exceptions during the day it's probably
okay you know just take care of myself
first
after all not Everyone likes these
pastries the way I do you know and uh
but what happens is over many years time
and and my wife is a great master of
this uh if you take care of other people
first
uh it's just really
amazing and it makes your life it makes
your whole life meaningful okay it like
whatever occupation you do with your
life doesn't matter whatever things you
study doesn't matter
whatever meditations you do doesn't
matter
just
focus on other people take care of them
first
if that's the only thing you learn at
Diamond Mountain Retreat Center then
your life is set okay just take care of
other people first
and and you'll have a super happy life
okay this struggle
to be happy
and take care of yourself first is a
losing battle okay you cannot it'll
never work it's a it's a stupid idea
it's a bad strategy
and it's Human Nature
so you have to fight it
not because of morality blah blah
because it's the only way to be happy
to take care of other people first so
the more you do it the happier you will
be
okay and you're not losing anything okay
you're losing something if you take it
first
then you lose it okay so
this attitude uh
there's a there's something about the
horse and the cowboy okay the horse is
your Prana your breathing
and the cowboy is your thoughts who's in
control
yes particularly I was you know I went
to Princeton and uh
I guess it was the second or third year
and somebody said
you know there's a
place near here there's a lake in
Princeton they built a lake
it's like Five Mile Lake that they built
Carnegie Andrew Carnegie built it and um
we used to race uh I was in the rowing
team
we used to race Up and Down the River
and
you could rent a horse and ride around
the river and uh
some of my friends said you want to rent
horses you're from Arizona right I'm
like oh yeah you know and uh I rode a
horse once you know it was his oldest
horse they could find
and uh I went out with my dad so I said
oh yeah I'm yeah I can do that so we
went out and uh
it was really funny because uh I saw
these cowboy movies where you kicked the
horse and you you know so I kicked the
horse you know and it goes
and then I'm like
I'm trying to stop the horse and then
the you know there's a sting in their
mouth and you pull it and and it hurt
you know and the Horse stopped
suddenly and I went
and just fall down okay and I never got
on a horse again in my whole life okay
uh
why am I talking about that uh sometimes
the horse runs the show
okay if the breathing gets out of whack
if the breathing gets shaky
uh the thoughts will follow you see if
the horse goes out of control the cowboy
is not running the show anymore the
horse is running the show
Okay so
so sometimes your mind controls your
primer
and sometimes your product controls your
mind okay
okay depends on who's in charge
sometimes the horse is in charge okay
sometimes the person is in charge
so it can go either way okay means
it can go either way if you let your
breath get out of control
your mind will follow
if you let your mind get out of control
your breath will follow
if your meditation is so bad
that you can't watch your mind
at least watch your breath
okay that's a physical thing it's much
easier to watch okay if you can't
control your mind
if your mind has the capacity
to get unhappy and take care of yourself
first
and you don't have the capacity
to watch your mind
which we all lose that capacity
that's to watch your breath learn to
watch your breath if the breath gets
crazy
you can
trust that the mind is following us okay
so watch your breath on a bad day when
you can't watch your mind
watch your breath and that'll the
condition of the horse will tell you the
condition of the writer okay got it
so it's a symbiotic
relationship it goes both ways okay very
important here okay
okay
[Music]
if you get uh very good at this what can
mean
can without the B
in tibetan
means a mistake or problem
means hey no problem
mayo and tea
uh can but with the B prefix letter it
means to ride a horse
got it so now you won't forget
so bsk b s k y o n means
uh ride your Prana
like a wise cowboy
okay ride your Prana like a wise company
language here
uh if you're good at
watching your breath
it'll be easier for you to ducks in
yumsy okay remember
that other people have equal rights to
happiness
and then switch your
switch taking care of yourself first
with taking care of other people first
and you won't lose anything don't think
you're gonna lose anything
it's a lifetime struggle
to take care of other people first
because there's this deep
Instinct that if I don't take it first I
won't get it
especially with pastries
okay so there's this deep deep feeling
that if I don't get mine first
and I let everybody else have theirs
first I won't get it you know and that's
a
that's the biggest mistake you can make
in your life okay okay take care of
other people first trust it
and you're not losing anything don't be
stupid
how did you get pastries in the first
place
you know be a smart pastry addict
you know keep giving them to other
people and you assure your supply
forever
okay it's it's just intelligent
self-interest right
okay
um language here
this is a very unusual word
uh tril de chambo means uh
huge machine
okay uh the word for machine and
tibetanus related to the word from
miracle like truku
and it means
this practice of taking other people
first
is like a huge machine in the background
of your life okay doing Tomlin
is in the Llama machepa which is where
it came from
is called the huge machine
and it just means it's just a happiness
production facility
okay it's a huge we passed that uh pecan
Factory on the way out here
uh in in Veronica yesterday Veronica
asked me what's gosh that looks
impressive what do they make there you
know and they it's this huge machine
that takes the skin off the nuts
separates the nuts from the shell
huge huge huge machine that's true deck
okay that's that's what they're calling
here they're comparing
to that machine
that
that's a Happiness Machine in your in
your life okay that to take care of
others first
to thong and learn
is a huge
machine that can bring you happiness
happiness production facility
Factory happiness Factory
I'm always looking for good names for
rock and roll bands right jack
corny okay all right
then uh we're gonna stop this class here
and we'll continue he he goes from there
into Tundra
okay in this innocent little lamb room
uh he's about to go into uh deep Tundra
so I know you're gonna come back for the
next class okay
all right